A question I'm often asked is,
السؤال الذي كثيرًا ما يُطرح علي هو :
where did I get my passion for human rights and justice?
من أين لي هذا الشغف بحقوق الإنسان والعدالة؟
It started early.
لقد بدأ هذا باكرًا.
I grew up in the west of Ireland,
لقد نشأتُ في غرب آيرلندا،
wedged between four brothers,
متوسطةً أربعةَ أشقاء،
two older than me and two younger than me.
اثنين يكبرانني وآخَرَين يصغرانني.
So of course I had to be interested in human rights,
ولذلك بطبيعة الحال كان علي أن أهتم بحقوق الإنسان،
and equality and justice,
والمساواة والعدالة،
and using my elbows!
واستخدام المرفقين!
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
And those issues stayed with me and guided me,
و هذه القضايا ظلت معي و أرشدتني،
and in particular,
وعلى وجه الخصوص،
when I was elected the first woman President of Ireland,
عندما انتخبتُ رئيسة جمهورية آيرلندا، كأول امرأة تتولى هذا المنصب
from 1990 to 1997.
في الفترة بين 1990-1997.
I dedicated my presidency
وقد سخّرتُ رئاستي
to having a space for those who felt marginalized on the island of Ireland,
لإيجاد مكان لأولئك الذين شعروا بالتهميش في جزيرة آيرلندا،
and bringing together communities from Northern Ireland
بالإضافة إلى الجمع بين المجتمعات في آيرلندا الشمالية
with those from the Republic,
و بقية مجتمعات الجمهورية،
trying to build peace.
في محاولة لبناء السلام.
And I went as the first Irish president to the United Kingdom
وقد ذهبت كأول رئيسة آيرلندية إلى المملكة المتحدة.
and met with Queen Elizabeth II,
والتقيت الملكة إليزابيث الثانية.
and also welcomed to my official residence --
وقد تم الترحيب بي أيضا في المقر الرسمي لإقامتي الرئاسية--
which we call "Áras an Uachtaráin," the house of the president --
وهو ما نسميه "Áras an Uachtaráin" ؛ بيت الرئيس -
members of the royal family,
حيث رحب بي أعضاء من العائلة المالكة،
including, notably, the Prince of Wales.
و في مقدمتهم أمير ويلز.
And I was aware that at the time of my presidency,
وكنت أدرك إبان رئاستي،
Ireland was a country beginning a rapid economic progress.
أن أيرلندا كانت بلدًا في مطلع تقدمه السريع اقتصاديًا.
We were a country that was benefiting from the solidarity of the European Union.
فقد كنا دولة تستفيد من تضامن الاتحاد الأوروبي.
Indeed, when Ireland first joined the European Union in 1973,
و في الواقع، عندما انضمت آيرلندا مباشرة إلى الاتحاد الأوروبي في عام 1973،
there were parts of the country that were considered developing,
كانت هناك أجزاء من البلاد تعد نامية،
including my own beloved native county, County Mayo.
بما في ذلك بلدتي الأم الحبيبة، في مقاطعة مايو.
I led trade delegations here to the United States,
كما قمتُ بقيادة الوفود التجارية إلى هنا في الولايات المتحدة،
to Japan, to India,
و إلى اليابان، و الهند،
to encourage investment, to help to create jobs,
لتشجيع الاستثمار، وللمساعدة في خلق فرص عمل،
to build up our economy,
من أجل بناء اقتصادنا،
to build up our health system, our education --
و بناء نظامنا الصحي و التعليم لدينا--
our development.
و تنميتنا.
What I didn't have to do as president
ما لم يكن واجبًا علي فعله بصفتي رئيسة
was buy land on mainland Europe,
هو أن أشتري أرضًا في يابسة قارة أوروبا ،
so that Irish citizens could go there because our island was going underwater.
كي يُتاح للمواطنين الآيرلنديين العيش هناك لأن جزيرتنا تغوص في الماء.
What I didn't have to think about,
و ما لم يكن علي التفكير فيه،
either as president or as a constitutional lawyer,
بصفتي رئيسة أو كمحامية دستورية ،
was the implications for the sovereignty of the territory
كان التفكير في الآثار المترتبة على سيادة البلد
because of the impact of climate change.
نتيجة لتأثير تغير المناخ.
But that is what President Tong, of the Republic of Kiribati,
ولكن هذا هو ما كان يستيقظ لأجله رئيس جمهورية كيريباتي، السيد تونغ
has to wake up every morning thinking about.
و يفكر فيه كل صباح.
He has bought land in Fiji as an insurance policy,
فقد اشترى أرضًا في جمهورية جزر فيجي كبوليصة تأمينية ،
what he calls, "migration with dignity,"
أو ما يسميه "الهجرة بكرامة،"
because he knows that his people may have to leave their islands.
لأنه يعلم أن شعبه قد يضطر إلى مغادرة جزرهم.
As I listened to President Tong describing the situation,
و عندما استمعت إلى الرئيس تونغ يصف الوضع،
I really felt that this was a problem that no leader should have to face.
شعرتُ حقًا أن هذه هي المشكلة التي لا يتوجب على أي زعيم مواجهتها.
And as I heard him speak about the pain of his problems,
و عندما سمعت صوته وهو يتحدث عن الألم بسبب مشاكله،
I thought about Eleanor Roosevelt.
تفكرتُ في إليانور روزفلت.
I thought about her and those who worked with her
فكرت فيها وفي أولئك الذين عملوا معها
on the Commission on Human Rights, which she chaired in 1948,
في لجنة حقوق الإنسان، التي ترأستها في عام 1948،
and drew up the Universal Declaration of Human Rights.
و التي صاغت الإعلان العالمي لحقوق الإنسان.
For them, it would have been unimaginable
بالنسبة لهم، فما لم يكن ممكنًا تصوره
that a whole country could go out of existence
هو أن بلدًا بأكمله يمكن أن يختفي من الوجود
because of human-induced climate change.
بسبب تغير المناخ الناتج عن أنشطة بشرية.
I came to climate change not as a scientist or an environmental lawyer,
أتحدث عن تغير المناخ ليس كعالمة أو محامية بيئية،
and I wasn't really impressed by the images of polar bears
ولم أبال حقًا بصور الدببة القطبية
or melting glaciers.
أو ذوبان الأنهار الجليدية.
It was because of the impact on people,
بل كان ذلك بسبب أثر تغير المناخ على الناس،
and the impact on their rights --
وأثر ذلك على حقوقهم --
their rights to food and safe water, health, education and shelter.
حقوقهم في الغذاء والمياه الصالحة للشرب، وفي الصحة والتعليم و المأوى.
And I say this with humility,
وأنا أقول هذا بكل تواضع،
because I came late to the issue of climate change.
لأنني اهتممت متأخرة بقضية تغير المناخ.
When I served
و عندما اشتغلت
as UN High Commissioner for Human Rights
مفوضةً سامية لحقوق الإنسان بالأمم المتحدة
from 1997 to 2002,
في الفترة من 1997 إلى 2002،
climate change wasn't at the front of my mind.
لم يكن تغير المناخ من أولوياتي.
I don't remember making a single speech on climate change.
و لا أتذكر أني قد ألقيت خطابًا واحدًا بشأن تغير المناخ.
I knew that there was another part of the United Nations --
و عرفتُ فيما بعد أن ثمة جزءا آخر في الأمم المتحدة --
the UN Convention on Climate Change --
و هو اتفاقية الأمم المتحدة بشأن تغير المناخ -
that was dealing with the issue of climate change.
التي اهتمامها قضية تغير المناخ.
It was later when I started to work in African countries
و في وقت لاحق بدأت العمل في البلدان الأفريقية
on issues of development and human rights.
في قضايا التنمية وحقوق الإنسان.
And I kept hearing this pervasive sentence:
وظللت أسمع هذه الجملة ذائعة الصيت:
"Oh, but things are so much worse now, things are so much worse."
"أوه، و لكن الأمور أسوأ من ذلك بكثير الآن، الأمور أسوأ كثيرا."
And then I explored what was behind that;
ثم بحثت عن سبب ذلك؛
it was about changes in the climate --
وقد كان عن التغيرات في المناخ --
climate shocks, changes in the weather.
الصدمات المناخية، والتغيرات في الطقس.
I met Constance Okollet,
التقيت كونستانس أوكولوت،
who had formed a women's group in Eastern Uganda,
التي شكلت مجموعة نسائية في أوغندا الشرقية،
and she told me that when she was growing up,
وقالت لي إنها عندما كبرت،
she had a very normal life in her village and they didn't go hungry,
عاشت حياة طبيعية جدا في قريتها، وأنهم لم يعانوا من الجوع،
they knew that the seasons would come as they were predicted to come,
حيث كانوا يعرفون أن المواسم ستأتي كما هو متوقع لها،
they knew when to sow and they knew when to harvest,
كانوا يعلمون متى يزرعون وكانوا يعرفون موسم الحصاد،
and so they had enough food.
وهكذا كان لديهم ما يكفي من الغذاء.
But, in recent years,
ولكن، في السنوات الأخيرة،
at the time of this conversation,
في وقت تلك المحادثة،
they had nothing but long periods of drought,
لم يكن لديهم شيء سوى أزمنة طويلة من الجفاف،
and then flash flooding,
ثم الفيضانات،
and then more drought.
ومن ثم مزيد من الجفاف.
The school had been destroyed,
دمرت المدارس،
livelihoods had been destroyed,
و سبل العيش،
their harvest had been destroyed.
و محاصيلهم.
She forms this women's group to try to keep her community together.
فأنشأت هذه المجموعة النسائية في محاولة للحفاظ على مجتمعهن معا.
And this was a reality that really struck me,
وكان هذا هو الواقع الذي أدهشني حقا،
because of course, Constance Okollet wasn't responsible
لأنه و بطبيعة الحال، لم تكن كونستانس أوكولوت مسؤولة
for the greenhouse gas emissions that were causing this problem.
عن الانبعاثات الغازية الدفيئة التي تتسبب في هذه المشكلة.
Indeed, I was very struck about the situation in Malawi
في الواقع، كنت مندهشة جدا بسبب الوضع في ملاوي
in January of this year.
في يناير من هذا العام.
There was an unprecedented flooding in the country,
كانت هناك فيضانات لم يسبق لها مثيل في البلاد،
it covered about a third of the country,
غطت نحو ثلث البلاد،
over 300 people were killed,
و قتلت أكثر من 300 شخصا ،
and hundreds of thousands lost their livelihoods.
وأفقدت مئات الآلاف مصادر رزقهم.
And the average person in Malawi
وإذا كان ينبعث من الشخص العادي في ملاوي
emits about 80 kg of CO2 a year.
من ثاني أكسيد الكربون نحو 80 كيلوغراما سنويا.
The average US citizen emits about 17.5 metric tons.
فإنه ينبعث من المواطن الأمريكي العادي نحو 17.5 طن متري.
So those who are suffering disproportionately
فحتى أولئك الذين يعانون بشكل متفاوت
don't drive cars, don't have electricity, don't consume very significantly,
لا يقودون السيارات، ولا يملكون الكهرباء، و لا يستهلكون بشكل كبير جدا،
and yet they are feeling more and more
و مع ذلك يشعرون أكثر وأكثر
the impacts of the changes in the climate,
بآثارالتغيرات في المناخ،
the changes that are preventing them from knowing how to grow food properly,
التغييرات التي تمنعهم من معرفة كيفية زراعة المحاصيل الغذائية بشكل صحيح،
and knowing how to look after their future.
ومعرفة كيفية الاعتناء بمستقبلهم.
I think it was really the importance of the injustice
وأعتقد أن ما أدهشني حقا كان أهمية الظلم
that really struck me very forcibly.
لقد أدهشني قسرا.
And I know that we're not able to address some of that injustice
وأنا أعلم أننا لسنا قادرين على معالجة بعضا من ذلك الظلم
because we're not on course for a safe world.
لأننا لسنا في طريقنا لعالم آمن.
Governments around the world agreed at the conference in Copenhagen,
فقد اتفقت الحكومات في جميع أنحاء العالم في مؤتمر كوبنهاغن،
and have repeated it at every conference on climate,
ولقد تكرر ذلك في كل مؤتمر حول المناخ،
that we have to stay below two degrees Celsius
أن علينا البقاء دون درجتين مئويتين
of warming above pre-Industrial standards.
عن مقياس درجة الحرارة ما قبل الصناعية.
But we're on course for about four degrees.
لكننا في الطريق نحو أربع درجات.
So we face an existential threat to the future of our planet.
لذلك نحن نواجه تهديدا وجوديا لمستقبل كوكبنا.
And that made me realize
وهذا جعلني أدرك
that climate change is the greatest threat to human rights in the 21st century.
أن تغير المناخ هو أكبر تهديد لحقوق الإنسان في القرن ال21.
And that brought me then to climate justice.
و هذا ما ولجت من خلاله إلى العدالة المناخية.
Climate justice responds to the moral argument --
العدالة المناخية هي ردة فعل على الجدل الأخلاقي-
both sides of the moral argument --
على كلي جانبي الجدل الأخلاقي--
to address climate change.
للتصدي لتغير المناخ.
First of all,
أولًا،
to be on the side of those who are suffering most and are most effected.
أن تكون في صف أولئك الذين يعانون ويتأثرون أكثر من غيرهم.
And secondly,
وثانيا،
to make sure that they're not left behind again, when we start to move
أن تتأكد من عدم تركهم بمفردهم مرة أخرى ، عندما نبدأ في التحرك
and start to address climate change with climate action,
و التصدي لتغير المناخ مع إجراءات عملية تخص المناخ،
as we are doing.
وهذا ما نفعله.
In our very unequal world today,
في عالمنا غير المتكافئ جدًا اليوم،
it's very striking how many people are left behind.
من الملفت جدا كم الأشخاص المهمشين.
In our world of 7.2 billion people, about 3 billion are left behind.
فهناك 3 مليارات من البشر منسيون من 7.2 من سكان العالم
1.3 billion don't have access to electricity,
و هناك 1.3 مليار لا يستطيعون الحصول على الكهرباء،
and they light their homes with kerosene and candles,
فيضطرون أن يضيؤوا منازلهم بالكيروسين والشموع،
both of which are dangerous.
وكلاهما خطر.
And in fact they spend a lot of their tiny income on that form of lighting.
في واقع الأمر أنهم ينفقون الكثير من دخلهم المحدود في هذا النوع من الإضاءة.
2.6 billion people cook on open fires --
و هناك 2.6 مليار شخص يطهون على النار المكشوفة -
on coal, wood and animal dung.
و على الفحم والخشب و روث الحيوانات.
And this causes about 4 million deaths a year
وهذا يسبب حوالي 4 ملايين حالة وفاة سنويا
from indoor smoke inhalation,
بسبب استنشاق الدخان في الأماكن المغلقة.
and of course, most of those who die are women.
وبطبيعة الحال، فإن معظم الذين يموتون هم من النساء.
So we have a very unequal world,
نعم لدينا عالم غير متساو للغاية،
and we need to change from "business as usual."
ونحن بحاجة إلى التغيير بدءًا من العبارة الروتينية "عمل كالمعتاد".
And we shouldn't underestimate the scale and the transformative nature
ويجب علينا ألا نقلل من قدر الطبيعة التحويلية للتغيير
of the change which will be needed,
و حجمه الذي ستكون هناك حاجة له.
because we have to go to zero carbon emissions by about 2050,
حيث أننا نطمح لتقليل الانبعاثات الكربونية إلى درجة صفر بحوالي عام 2050،
if we're going to stay below two degrees Celsius of warming.
هذا إن أردنا السير نحو هدفنا و هو البقاء تحت مستوى أقل من درجتين مئويتين .
And that means we have to leave about two-thirds of the known resources
وهذا يعني أن علينا أن ترك حوالي ثلثي الموارد المعروفة
of fossil fuels in the ground.
من الوقود الأحفوري في الأرض.
It's a very big change,
إنه لتغيير كبير جدا،
and it means that obviously,
وهذا يعني أنه يجب على
industrialized countries must cut their emissions,
الدول الصناعية وبكل وضوح خفض انبعاثاتها،
must become much more energy-efficient,
و أن تصبح أكثر كفاءة من حيث الطاقة،
and must move as quickly as possible to renewable energy.
وأن تتحرك بأسرع وقت ممكن لحل الطاقة المتجددة.
For developing countries and emerging economies,
و بالنسبة للدول النامية و الاقتصادات الناشئة،
the problem and the challenge is to grow without emissions,
فإن المشكلة والتحدي لها هو أن تنمو دون مشاكل الانبعاثات،
because they must develop; they have very poor populations.
حيث يجب أن تتطور فالسكان فيها يعانون من الفقر كثيرًا.
So they must develop without emissions, and that is a different kind of problem.
لذلك يجب أن تتطور دون انبعاثات، وهذا هو جانب مختلف للمشكلة.
Indeed, no country in the world has actually grown without emissions.
ففي الواقع أنه لا يوجد بلد في العالم قد نما دون انبعاثات.
All the countries have developed with fossil fuels,
إذ أن جميع البلدان تطورت بالوقود الأحفوري،
and then may be moving to renewable energy.
ومن ثم يمكن لها الانتقال إلى الطاقة المتجددة.
So it is a very big challenge,
لذلك يشكل هذا تحديا كبيرا للغاية،
and it requires the total support of the international community,
و يتطلب المساندة الكاملة من المجتمع الدولي،
with the necessary finance and technology, and systems and support,
و ذلك بالتمويل اللازم و التقنية، و الأنظمة و الدعم.
because no country can make itself safe from the dangers of climate change.
حيث لا يوجد بلد يمكن أن يكون في مأمن من مخاطر تغير المناخ.
This is an issue that requires complete human solidarity.
هذه مسألة تتطلب التضامن الإنساني الكامل.
Human solidarity, if you like, based on self-interest --
وهذا التضامن الإنساني، إن أحببت القول، يعتمد على المصلحة الذاتية -
because we are all in this together,
لأننا نشترك جميعا في هذا ،
and we have to work together
وعلينا أن نعمل معا
to ensure that we reach zero carbon by 2050.
للتأكد من وصولنا إلى نسبة صفر من انبعاثات الكربون بحلول عام 2050.
The good news is that change is happening,
والخبر السار هو أن التغيير يحدث،
and it's happening very fast.
ويحدث بسرعة كبيرة.
Here in California,
هنا في ولاية كاليفورنيا،
there's a very ambitious emissions target to cut emissions.
هناك هدف طموح جدًا للحد من الانبعاثات.
In Hawaii, they're passing legislation
و في هاواي، يقومون بسن التشريعات
to have 100 percent renewable energy by 2045.
بغية امتلاك الطاقة المتجددة بنسبة 100% بحلول عام 2045.
And governments are very ambitious around the world.
والحكومات في جميع أنحاء العالم طموحة جدا بهذا الخصوص.
In Costa Rica, they have committed to being carbon-neutral by 2021.
و في كوستاريكا، التزموا بخلوها من الكربون بحلول عام 2021.
In Ethiopia, the commitment is to be carbon-neutral by 2027.
, في إثيوبيا، تم الالتزام بأن تكون خالية من الكربون بحلول عام 2027.
Apple have pledged that their factories in China will use renewable energy.
كما تعهدت شركة آبل بأن تستعمل مصانعها في الصين الطاقة المتجددة.
And there is a race on at the moment
وهناك سباق جار في الوقت الراهن
to convert electricity from tidal and wave power,
لتحول الكهرباء من طاقة المد والجزر والأمواج،
in order that we can leave the coal in the ground.
من أجل أن نتمكن من ترك الفحم في باطن الأرض.
And that change is both welcome and is happening very rapidly.
وهذا التغيير هو أمرٌ مرحب به كما أنه يحدث بشكل سريع جدا.
But it's still not enough,
لكن هذا ليس كافيًا.
and the political will is still not enough.
والرغبة السياسية لا تكفي.
Let me come back to President Tong and his people in Kiribati.
اسمحوا لي أن أعود إلى الرئيس تونغ وشعبه في كيريباتي.
They actually could be able to live on their island and have a solution,
كان بالإمكان أن يعيشوا في جزيرتهم وأن يجدوا حلا للمشكلة ،
but it would take a lot of political will.
ولكن الأمر يقتضي رغبة سياسية قوية .
President Tong told me about his ambitious idea
وقد حدثني الرئيس تونغ عن فكرته الطموحة
to either build up or even float the little islands where his people live.
وهي بناء جزرهم الصغيرة التي يعيش فيها شعبه أو تركها تطفو.
This, of course, is beyond the resources of Kiribati itself.
هذا، بطبيعة الحال، هو أبعد من موارد كيريباتي نفسها.
It would require great solidarity and support from other countries,
فإن ذلك يتطلب تضامنا كبيرا ودعما من دول أخرى،
and it would require the kind of imaginative idea
وذلك يتطلب هذا النوع من فكرة مبدعة
that we bring together when we want to have a space station in the air.
أن نأتي معا عندما كنا نريد أن يكون محطة الفضاء في الهواء.
But wouldn't it be wonderful to have this engineering wonder
لكن لن يكون من الرائع أن يكون هذا عجب الهندسة
and to allow a people to remain in their sovereign territory,
والسماح للشعب بالبقاء في أراضيها السيادية،
and be part of the community of nations?
وتكون جزءا من المجتمع الدولي؟
That is the kind of idea that we should be thinking about.
هذا هو نوع من فكرة أننا يجب أن يكون التفكير.
Yes, the challenges of the transformation we need are big,
نعم، تحديات التحول نحتاج كبيرة،
but they can be solved.
ولكن يمكن حلها.
We are actually, as a people,
نحن في الواقع، كشعب،
very capable of coming together to solve problems.
قادرة جدا القادمة معا من أجل حل المشاكل.
I was very conscious of this as I took part this year
كنت واعية جدا لهذا وأنا شاركت هذا العام
in commemoration of the 70th anniversary
في الاحتفال بالذكرى السنوية الـ70
of the end of the Second World War in 1945.
من نهاية الحرب العالمية الثانية في عام 1945.
1945 was an extraordinary year.
1945 كان عاما استثنائيا.
It was a year when the world faced
لقد كانت سنة عندما واجه العالم
what must have seemed almost insoluble problems --
ما يجب أن يكون بدا المشاكل غير قابلة للذوبان تقريبا -
the devastation of the world wars, particularly the Second World War;
الدمار الذي خلفته الحروب العالمية، وخاصة الحرب العالمية الثانية؛
the fragile peace that had been brought about;
السلام الهش الذي كان قد أحدثت؛
the need for a whole economic regeneration.
الحاجة إلى تجديد الاقتصادي كله.
But the leaders of that time didn't flinch from this.
لكن قادة ذلك الوقت لم تتوانى عن ذلك.
They had the capacity, they had a sense of being driven by
كان لديهم القدرة، كان لديهم شعور يقودها
never again must the world have this kind of problem.
أبدا مرة أخرى يجب على العالم أن يكون هذا النوع من المشاكل.
And they had to build structures for peace and security.
وكان عليهم أن بناء هياكل للسلام والأمن.
And what did we get? What did they achieve?
وماذا حصلنا عليه؟ ما لم نحققه؟
The Charter of the United Nations,
ميثاق الأمم المتحدة،
the Bretton Woods institutions, as they're called, The World Bank,
مؤسسات بريتون وودز، كما انهم يسمى، البنك الدولي،
and the International Monetary Fund.
وصندوق النقد الدولي.
A Marshall Plan for Europe, a devastated Europe,
خطة مارشال لأوروبا، أوروبا المدمرة،
to reconstruct it.
لإعادة بنائه.
And indeed a few years later,
وفي وقت لاحق بالفعل بضع سنوات،
the Universal Declaration of Human Rights.
الإعلان العالمي لحقوق الإنسان.
2015 is a year that is similar in its importance
2015 هو عام مشابه في أهميته
to 1945, with similar challenges and similar potential.
وحتى عام 1945، مع تحديات مماثلة وإمكانية مماثلة.
There will be two big summits this year:
سيكون هناك قمتين كبيرة هذا العام:
the first one, in September in New York,
أول واحدة، في سبتمبر في نيويورك،
is the summit for the sustainable development goals.
هو قمة لأهداف التنمية المستدامة.
And then the summit in Paris in December, to give us a climate agreement.
ثم قمة في باريس في ديسمبر، ليقدم لنا اتفاق المناخ.
The sustainable development goals are intended to help countries
والغرض من أهداف التنمية المستدامة لمساعدة البلدان
to live sustainably, in tune with Mother Earth,
للعيش على نحو مستدام، في تناغم مع الأرض الأم،
not to take out of Mother Earth and destroy ecosystems,
لا تأخذ من الأرض الأم وتدمير النظم الإيكولوجية،
but rather, to live in harmony with Mother Earth,
ولكن بدلا من ذلك، أن يعيش في وئام مع الأرض الأم،
by living under sustainable development.
من قبل الذين يعيشون تحت التنمية المستدامة.
And the sustainable development goals
وأهداف التنمية المستدامة
will come into operation for all countries
ستدخل حيز التنفيذ بالنسبة لجميع البلدان
on January 1, 2016.
في 1 يناير 2016.
The climate agreement --
اتفاق المناخ -
a binding climate agreement --
اتفاق ملزم المناخ -
is needed because of the scientific evidence
وهناك حاجة لأدلة علمية
that we're on a trajectory for about a four-degree world
اننا على مسار نحو عالم أربعة درجة-
and we have to change course to stay below two degrees.
وعلينا أن تغيير المسار للبقاء أقل من درجتين.
So we need to take steps that will be monitored and reviewed,
لذلك نحن بحاجة إلى اتخاذ الخطوات التي سيتم رصدها واستعراضها،
so that we can keep increasing the ambition of how we cut emissions,
حتى نتمكن من الحفاظ على زيادة طموح كيف يمكننا خفض الانبعاثات،
and how we move more rapidly to renewable energy,
وكيف نتحرك بسرعة أكبر على الطاقة المتجددة،
so that we have a safe world.
حتى يكون لدينا عالم آمن.
The reality is that this issue is much too important
والحقيقة هي أن هذه المسألة هي أهم من ذلك بكثير
to be left to politicians and to the United Nations.
لتترك للسياسيين وللأمم المتحدة.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
It's an issue for all of us,
إنها مشكلة بالنسبة لنا جميعا،
and it's an issue where we need more and more momentum.
وهي مسألة نحتاج فيها المزيد والمزيد من الزخم.
Indeed, the face of the environmentalist has changed,
في الواقع، وجه البيئة قد تغيرت،
because of the justice dimension.
بسبب البعد العدالة.
It's now an issue for faith-based organizations,
إنها الآن تمثل مشكلة بالنسبة للمنظمات الدينية،
under very good leadership from Pope Francis,
تحت قيادة جيدة جدا من البابا فرانسيس،
and indeed, the Church of England,
وبالفعل، فإن كنيسة إنكلترا،
which is divesting from fossil fuels.
وهو تجريد من الوقود الأحفوري.
It's an issue for the business community,
إنها قضية لمجتمع الأعمال،
and the good news is
والخبر السار هو
that the business community is changing very rapidly --
إن مجتمع الأعمال يتغير بسرعة جدا -
except for the fossil fuel industries --
باستثناء الصناعات الوقود الأحفوري -
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
Even they are beginning to slightly change their language --
حتى أنها بدأت في تغيير طفيف لغتهم -
but only slightly.
ولكن بشكل طفيف.
But business is not only moving rapidly to the benefits of renewable energy,
ولكن العمل ليس فقط تتحرك بسرعة لفوائد الطاقة المتجددة،
but is urging politicians to give them more signals,
ولكن تحث السياسيين لمنحهم المزيد من الاشارات،
so that they can move even more rapidly.
بحيث يمكن أن تتحرك بسرعة أكبر.
It's an issue for the trade union movement.
انها مسألة تخص الحركة النقابية.
It's an issue for the women's movement.
إنها قضية للحركة النسائية.
It's an issue for young people.
إنها قضية للشباب.
I was very struck when I learned that Jibreel Khazan,
دهشت جدا عندما علمت أن جبريل الخزان،
one of the Greensboro Four who had taken part in the Woolworth sit-ins,
واحدة من أربع جرينسبورو الذين شاركوا في ولوورث الاعتصامات،
said quite recently that
وقال قريب جدا أن
climate change is the lunch counter moment for young people.
تغير المناخ هو مكافحة هذه اللحظة غداء للشباب.
So, lunch counter moment for young people of the 21st century --
لذلك، ومكافحة الغداء حظة للشباب في القرن ال21 -
the sort of real human rights issue of the 21st century,
هذا النوع من القضية الحقيقية في القرن الـ21 حقوق الإنسان،
because he said it is the greatest challenge
لأنه قال ذلك هو التحدي الأكبر
to humanity and justice in our world.
للإنسانية والعدالة في عالمنا.
I recall very much the Climate March last September,
وأذكر كثيرا حركة كلايمت مارش سبتمبر الماضي،
and that was a huge momentum,
وكان ذلك الزخم الهائل،
not just in New York, but all around the world.
ليس فقط في نيويورك، ولكن في جميع أنحاء العالم.
and we have to build on that.
وعلينا أن نبني على ذلك.
I was marching with some of The Elders family,
كنت يسيرون مع بعض شيوخ الأسرة،
and I saw a placard a little bit away from me,
ورأيت لافتة قليلا بعيدا عني،
but we were wedged so closely together --
لكننا كنا جبالا ذلك معا بشكل وثيق -
because after all, there were 400,000 people out in the streets of New York --
لأنه بعد كل شيء، كان هناك 400،000 شخص في شوارع نيويورك -
so I couldn't quite get to that placard,
لذلك لم أتمكن من الوصول تماما لتلك اللافتة،
I would have just liked to have been able to step behind it,
كنت أتمنى فقط أن أكون قادرة على السير وراءها،
because it said, "Angry Grannies!"
لقول ذلك "جدات غاضبات!"
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
That's what I felt.
هذا ما شعرت به.
And I have five grandchildren now,
ولدي خمسة أحفاد الآن،
I feel very happy as an Irish grandmother to have five grandchildren,
أشعر بسعادة كبيرة جدا باعتباري جدة ايرلندية لخمسة أحفاد،
and I think about their world,
وأفكر في عالمهم،
and what it will be like when they will share that world
وماذا سيكون عليه الحال بمشاركتهم هذا العالم
with about 9 billion other people in 2050.
مع حوالي 9 مليار نسمة أخرى في عام 2050.
We know that inevitably it will be a climate-constrained world,
ونحن نعلم أن حتما أنه سيكون عالم مقيد بالمناخ،
because of the emissions we've already put up there,
بسبب انبعاثات قد وضعناها في العالم بالفعل،
but it could be a world that is much more equal and much fairer,
ولكن يمكن أن يكون عالما أكثر مساواة بكثير وأكثر عدلا،
and much better for health, and better for jobs
وأفضل بكثير للصحة، وأفضل من حيث الوظائف
and better for energy security,
وأفضل لأمن الطاقة،
than the world we have now,
من العالم الذي نعيشه الآن،
if we have switched sufficiently and early enough to renewable energy,
إذا كنا قد تحولت بشكل كاف ومطلع على الطاقة المتجددة،
and no one is left behind.
وعدم إغفال أحد.
No one is left behind.
سيكون كل شخص قد أثخذ في الإعتبار.
And just as we've been looking back this year --
وتماما كما كنا ننظر الى الوراء هذا العام -
in 2015 to 1945, looking back 70 years --
في 2015-1945، إذا نظرنا إلى الوراء 70 عاما -
I would like to think that they will look back,
وأود أن أعتقد أنهم سينظرون إلى الماضي،
that world will look back 35 years from 2050,
أن العالم سينظر إلى الماضي 35 عاما من عام 2050،
35 years to 2015,
35 سنوات لعام 2015،
and that they will say,
وأنهم سوف يقولون،
"Weren't they good to do what they did in 2015?
"ألم يكن من الأفضل القيام بما فعلوه في عام 2015؟
We really appreciate that they took the decisions that made a difference,
نحن نقدر حقا أنهم اتخذوا القرارات التي أحدثت فرقا،
and that put the world on the right pathway,
والتي وضعت العالم على المسار الصحيح،
and we benefit now from that pathway,"
ونحن الآن نستفيد من هذا المسار"
that they will feel that somehow we took our responsibilities,
و أنهم سوف يشعرون بأننا بطريقة ما راعينا مسؤولياتنا،
we did what was done in 1945 in similar terms,
فعلنا ما حدث في عام 1945 من ظروف مماثلة،
we didn't miss the opportunity,
نحن لم نفوت الفرصة،
we lived up to our responsibilities.
قمنا بتحمل مسؤولياتنا.
That's what this year is about.
و هذا هو الهدف هذه السنة.
And somehow for me,
وعلى نحو ما بالنسبة لي،
it's captured in words of somebody that I admired very much.
أجد هذا متمثلًا في كلام شخص ما أنا معجبة به كثيرا.
She was a mentor of mine, she was a friend,
وكانت معلمتي و صديقتي،
she died much too young,
توفيت صغيرة جدًا ،
she was an extraordinary personality,
كانت شخصية غير عادية،
a great champion of the environment:
البطلة العظيمة للبيئة:
Wangari Maathai.
قالت أنجاري ماثاي.
Wangari said once,
قالت مرة:
"In the course of history,
"في مسار التاريخ،
there comes a time when humanity is called upon
يأتي على الناس زمان تُدعى فيه الإنسانية
to shift to a new level of consciousness,
إلى التحول إلى مستوى أعلى من الوعي،
to reach a higher moral ground."
و للسعي إلى أرضية أخلاقية عليا."
And that's what we have to do.
وهذا ما يتعين علينا القيام به.
We have to reach a new level of consciousness,
علينا الوصول إلى مستوى جديد من الوعي،
a higher moral ground.
من أرضية أخلاقية أسمى.
And we have to do it this year in those two big summits.
ويتعين علينا القيام بهذا هذا العام في هاتين القمتين الكبرتين.
And that won't happen unless we have the momentum
وهذا لن يحدث إلا إذا كان لدينا زخم
from people around the world who say:
من الناس في جميع أنحاء العالم الذين يقولون:
"We want action now,
"نريد العمل الآن،
we want to change course,
نريد تغيير المسار،
we want a safe world,
نريد عالما آمنا،
a safe world for future generations,
عالما آمنا للأجيال القادمة،
a safe world for our children and our grandchildren,
عالما آمنا لأبنائنا وأحفادنا،
and we're all in this together."
ونحن جميعا في هذا معا ".
Thank you.
شكرًا.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)